{
  "reference_number": "2080",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "We should have acted on climate change 30 years ago, any further delays are simply adding to the cost!"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We are only now experiencing the change caused by emissions from 30 and 40 years ago, we have to reduce emissions at all costs!"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should not buy into carbon units."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We should be able to act sooner if practicalities dictate."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Successive governments cannot be allowed to derail the process to reduce emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We have to allow for exceptional circumstances"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We have to understand that a short term economic impact is to be expected in return for a long term gain. The more we delay, the\ngreater the overall cost will be."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Looking at all possibilities to reduce emissions including potentially changing our primary industries in order to meet those budgets.\n\nThe need to reduce animal agriculture is clear and by increasing our horticultural products we will be offsetting our other emissions.\nWe also need to stop investing in fossil fuels and stop all permits for further ff exploration. We already cannot afford to burn what is\n\nhere now, we must stop squandering more money in the wrong places!"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation is vital, as this will be the hardest bit!"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "It must be fully independent without successive governments being able to change the goal posts. It must be decided on scientific\n\nbasis only."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Do not allow those whose business is creating climate change to complain about the loss of their profits as a result of actions to\ncombat climate change. That is a dying economy and we cannot allow it to continue to have it's say."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Vital."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We need to have joined up thinking in our plans to manage climate change. It needs to be global action too. NZ could lead the way,\n\nwe could have a purely organic horticultural economy and be the food basket for Asia as well as our local economy. We could go\n100% renewable power etc"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Again if we do not, we will miss some vital information. Ministers must be told the truth, we need to know the reality of our situation,\n\nnot be lulled into comforting lies."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "NZ could be a world leader in adapting to climate change. We could be implementing solar panels on all public buildings, reducing our\n\npower need nationwide, we could be investing in public transport in our cities, making cars an unaffordable luxury. We could improve\nworking conditions so those who could work from home, do so, reducing the need for a daily commute. The greening of public\n\nbuildings and open spaces would mitigate our pollution, the improvement in our recycling would reduce our need for new raw\nmaterials. We need to become more self-sufficient, Community gardens a must-have, fruit trees grown in public spaces,\nencouragement of vegetable gardens for all who want to grow their own.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
